Collective insight is the experience of
a group of people working together all
having the same key insight at the same
time although one or two individuals
might speak at first each person
experiences the insight the aha moment
spontaneously and at the same time so
there is very little impression that one
or another individual came up with the
idea on the contrary people report the
feeling of already knowing what the
person was going to say or alternately
the feeling of having someone taking the
words right out of their mouth
collective insight can be compared to a
group of musicians from different bands
and different styles coming to play
together at first they are each playing
in their own sound so it just sounds
like an arbitrary mix of competing ribs
but as they search for a sound that is
completely new the result goes through
phases of dissonance and experiment but
without any previous idea of what the
result will be and without needing
anything like agreement or consensus on
this form of that the group can
spontaneously shift and start to settle
into a completely new sound something
that surprises even them together they
begin to hear the form that is shaping
that is moving them toward an emergent
new way of play
we already know quite a few things about
collective insight we know it is a
special and rare outcome of group
interaction we know that collective
insight is emergent embody creative
spontaneous imaginative playful and
powerful and although most people have
difficulty describing it every person
knows it when they experience it in fact
even outside observers who come in after
the fact can tell when a group has
achieved collective insight we know that
collective insight is powerful because
it taps into creativity that is greater
than the sum total of the individuals in
the group we know that it depends upon
people in the group having a sufficient
orientation toward letting go of their
individual patterns of behavior thinking
doing and saying while also being
willing to abandon what they know in
lieu of what they might be surprised to
learn we know it depends upon the people
being able to allow themselves to flow
with emotional dialogic conceptual and
relational movements through all kinds
of phases and in any in all directions
we know that collective insight requires
the ability to stick with the engagement
during the oftentimes long process of
working through the uncomfortable
periods when nothing seems to be
happening or everything seems to be
going wrong we know that these are
periods which are very similar to
natural adaptive processes in which many
configurations of outcomes are tried but
few achieve the right fit or resonance
in these periods a bright idea might
fizzle out while deep silence or dark
tension might spark a wave of
inspiration we know that the process
depends strongly on relational dynamics
in that relational dynamics are
nonlinear and rye
strong waves of emotional energy and
subtle energetics and finally we know
that it is impossible to determine what
is a beneficial contribution from what
is not since everything that happens
contributes to the adaptive process
which can benefit from contributions
that can feel Pleasant or unpleasant and
that therefore the greatest potential
for collective insight happens in groups
where people learn to be clan amiss with
the process and happy to participate
without expectation of outcome for a
little more than 20 years small groups
of people around the world have been
experimenting with different versions of
collective engagement some of the
earliest attempts at group alignment
such as World Cafe focused on forms of
outward communication and forms of
presentation with the introduction of
Otto sharma's you Theory the focus
turned toward the quality of the
internal state or presence of the
individuals participating in group
activities Rhea Beck has carried this
into the practice of collective
presences Terry O'Fallon's gtc program
focuses on the role of higher
developmental stages and states of
awareness and more recently Terry Patton
has coined the term trans rhetorical and
others have used the term generative
discourse to signify a new type of
discourse that leads to or arises within
groups that practice a kind of
transpersonal interbeing and still other
practices rely on subtle states of
spiritual arousal that open and deepen
awareness of a kind of trans individual
being as reported by the core
practitioners of enlightened next
almost all these practices have taken
place within groups that self select
based on community needs shared values
or spiritual commitments we can consider
these practices as community specific
community specific practices are in some
sense primed by specialized language
shared means formal and sometimes
rigorous rules of engagement whether
explicitly stated or operating
implicitly while these conditions
maintain group cohesion they can also
intensify peer pressure and create false
consciousness all the people
participating in this symposium have
been careful to delineate specific
approaches that steer clear of the
conventional traps of collective
practice this symposium brings these
traditions together for the first time
to engage as peers all on the same level
all in the same suit to practice
collective insight the practice we will
perform will not decrease state it but
must arise from the co-creative an
emergent fermentation process in other
words the form of the practice must
arise from a kind of fermentation of
what we will bring individually and
collectively to the engagement we will
be open to being surprised and welcome
what will come this is both a
challenging and exciting prospect what
will we find out about ourselves what
will we witness about the process of
engaging as peers what principles of
collective practice will we discover
what significant insights will come in
the spontaneous co-creative relational
dance that will course there are four
days together if we can derive principle
for generating collective insight in
groups where there are few selection
criteria and where people represent a
broad range of values and oftentimes
competing worldviews then we have a
powerful practice for addressing 21st
century problems how often are our
communities our businesses our
organizations are government's stymied
by dysfunctional means of discourse in
pathological ways of being together
relational dynamics are more often
destructive than generative in these
groups especially where the topics are
complex and the stakes are very high if
we can set out a rigorous set of
principles for collective insight that
is not values or a worldview specific
but is methodological in scope and
process oral and practice then we have
the possibility of bringing collective
insight training into a much larger
context